Frank Maloy Anderson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frank Maloy Anderson Papers 1895-1961
MSS10934
Anderson, Frank Maloy, 1871-1961
40,000 items 57 containers 24 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, historian, and educator. Correspondence, memorabilia, and research notes for Anderson’s books, articles, lectures, and classes, especially in preparation for an unfinished study of the secession crisis, "The Two Hundred Days of 1860-1861."
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Anderson, Frank Maloy, 1871-1961.; Ward, Samuel, 1814-1884.
Subjects
Diplomacy.; International relations--History.; Secession--Southern States.
Places
Africa--Foreign relations.; Asia--Foreign relations.; Europe--Foreign relations.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Historians.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Frank Maloy Anderson, author, historian, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by his son, Gaylord Anderson, in 1960-1962.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Frank Maloy Anderson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1871, Feb. 3 Born, Omaha, Nebr.
1894 B.A., University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn.
1895 Edited with Charles L. Wells Outlines and Documents of English Constitutional History during the Middle Ages. Minneapolis: University Book Store
1895-1896 Taught, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn.
1896-1897 Student, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1897-1914 Taught history, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn.
1898 Married Mary G. Steele (died 1939)
1904 Published Constitutions and other Select Documents Illustrative of the History of France, 1789-1901. Minneapolis: H. W. Wilson Co.
1914-1941 Taught history, Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H.
1917-1920 Member, Executive Council, American Association of University Professors
1918 Published with Amos Shartle Hershey Handbook for the Diplomatic History of Europe, Asia, and Africa, 1870-1914. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office
1919 Attached to American Commission to Negotiate Peace, Paris, France
1926-1928 Member, Executive Council, American Historical Association
1941-1961 At work on "The Two Hundred Days of 1860-1861"
1944 Married Mary Maud Case
1948 Published Mystery of a "Public Man," a Historical Detective Story. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press
1961, Apr. 26 Died, St. Paul, Minn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frank Maloy Anderson (1871-1961) span the years circa 1895-circa 1961 and consist of correspondence, memorabilia, and an extensive file of research notes for books, studies, articles, and lectures organized within two series: General Correspondence and Related Material and Speech, Article, and Book File.
The bulk of the collection consists of research notes that Anderson prepared and collected over a twenty-year period in preparation for a three-volume study of the secession crisis, "The Two Hundred Days of 1860-1861," which remained unwritten at his death. The source notes are drawn from collections of personal papers, archives, newspapers, and books. The collection also includes a draft of an introduction to the study presenting a statement of Anderson's thesis and a proposed outline for the work. The papers further contain research notes for two of his published works, Mystery of a “Public Man" and Handbook for the Diplomatic History of Europe, Asia, and Africa, 1870-1914, as well as miscellaneous notes for lectures, classes, articles, and papers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in two series:
General Correspondence and Related Material, 1899-1954
Speech, Article, and Book File, circa 1895-circa 1961
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81010934
Container List
- General Correspondence and Related Material, 1899-1954 (Box 1)
  Correspondence, memorabilia, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1899-1954 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1)
- Speech, Article, and Book File, circa 1895-circa 1961 (Box 1-57)
  Research notes gathered by Anderson in support of his books, studies, articles, and lectures.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - "The Two Hundred Days of 1860-1861," unpublished study (Box 1)
    - Introduction, drafts and copies (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 1)
    - Reference notes, part I (1860, Nov. 6-Dec. 3) (Box 2)
      - Business (Box 2)
      - Newspapers (Box 2)
      - Republicans (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Personal papers (Box 3)
      - Persons (Box 3)
      - Cotton states (Box 4)
      - Election night (Box 4)
      - Northern feelings (Box 4)
      - Personal liberty laws (Box 4)
      - Proposal that Abraham Lincoln issue proclamation placating the South (Box 4)
      - Southern feelings (Box 4)
      - Border states (Box 5)
      - Mississippi (Box 5)
      - South Carolina (Box 5)
      - Virginia (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous states (Box 6)
    - Reference notes, part II (1860, Dec. 4-27) (Box 7)
      - Miscellany (Box 7)
      - Newspapers (Box 8)
      - Reconstruction (Box 8)
      - Republicans (Box 8)
      - Anderson's removal (Box 9)
      - Andrew Johnson's senate speech (Box 9)
      - Northern beliefs (Box 9)
      - Personal liberty laws (Box 9)
      - Persons (Box 9)
      - Correspondence (Box 10)
      - Corwin Committee (Box 10)
      - Cotton states (Box 10)
      - Miscellany (Box 11-13)
    - Reference notes, part III (1860, Dec. 28-1861, Feb. 4) (Box 14)
      - Commissions and missions (Box 14)
      - Newspapers (Box 14)
      - States (Box 14)
      - Compromise proposals (Box 15)
      - Corwin Committee (Box 15)
      - Personal liberty laws (Box 15)
      - Persons (Box 15)
      - Correspondence (Box 16)
      - Northern beliefs (Box 16)
      - Seward's senate speech (Box 16)
      - Southern beliefs (Box 16)
      - Star of the West (ship) (Box 16)
      - Miscellany (Box 17-20)
    - Reference notes, part IV (1861, Feb. 4-Mar. 4) (Box 21)
      - Davis, Jefferson (Box 21)
      - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 21)
      - Lincoln's journey (Box 21)
      - Persons (Box 21)
      - Republican Party (Box 21)
      - Fort Sumter (Box 22)
      - Lincoln's cabinet (Box 22)
      - States (Box 22)
      - Compromise proposals (Box 23)
      - Personal papers (Box 23)
      - Washington Peace Convention (Box 23)
      - Correspondence (Box 24)
      - Newspapers (Box 24)
      - Reconstruction (Box 24)
      - Congress (Box 25)
      - Missions (Box 25)
      - Montgomery, Ala. (Box 25)
      - Northern beliefs (Box 25)
      - Personal liberty laws (Box 25)
      - Southern beliefs (Box 25)
      - Speeches (Box 25)
      - Washington, D.C. (Box 25)
    - Reference notes, part V (1861, Mar. 5-Apr. 4) (Box 26)
      - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 26)
      - Newspapers (Box 26)
      - Fort Sumter (Box 27)
      - Northern beliefs (Box 27)
      - Southern beliefs (Box 27)
      - Correspondence (Box 28)
      - Fort Pickens (Box 28)
      - Persons (Box 28)
      - Speeches (Box 28)
      - States (Box 28)
      - Virginia (Box 28)
      - Border states (Box 29)
      - Cabinet (Box 29)
      - Confederate Commissioners in Washington (Box 29)
      - Congress (Box 29)
      - Miscellany (Box 29)
      - Personal papers (Box 29)
    - Reference notes, part VI (1861, Apr. 5-15) (Box 30)
      - Fort Sumter crisis (Box 30)
      - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 30)
      - States (Box 30)
      - Chronological file ("by date" file) (Box 31)
      - Correspondence (Box 31)
      - Miscellany (Box 31)
      - Newspapers (Box 31)
    - Reference notes, part VII (1861, Apr. 15-May 24) (Box 32)
      - Border states (Box 32)
      - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 32)
      - Lincoln's proclamation (Box 32)
      - Newspapers (Box 32)
      - Correspondence (Box 33)
      - Hopes, plans, and possibilities for peace (Box 33)
      - Personal papers (Box 33)
      - States and cities (Box 33)
      - Washington, D.C (Box 33)
      - Chronological file ("dated events" file) (Box 34)
      - Miscellany (Box 34)
      - Northern beliefs (Box 34)
      - Persons (Box 34)
      - Southern beliefs (Box 34)
    - Reference notes, undated (Box 35)
      - Anderson, Robert (Box 35)
      - Holt Papers (Box 35)
      - Miscellaneous personal papers (Box 35)
      - Seward, William Henry, papers (Box 35)
      - Sherman, William T., papers (Box 35)
      - Chronological files (Box 36)
        - 1860-1861 (Box 36)
        - Prior to 1860, Nov. 6 (Box 36)
        - After 1861, May 24 (Box 37)
      - Miscellany (Box 37)
      - Research reminders (Box 38)
  - Mystery of a "Public Man" (Box 39)
    - Commentary on diary (Box 39)
    - Reference notes (Box 39)
      - Hurlbert, W. H. (Box 39)
      - King, Horatio (Box 39)
      - Ward, Sam (Box 39)
      - Wickoff, Henry (Box 39)
    - Miscellany (Box 40)
  - Handbook for the Diplomatic History of Europe, Asia, and Africa, 1870-1914 (Box 41)
    - Reference notes for chapters (Box 41)
      - Chapters 1-43 (Box 41)
      - Chapters 44-45 (Box 42)
      - Chapters 45-49, 52-100 (Box 43)
      - Chapters 103-160 (Box 44)
    - Reference notes, miscellaneous (Box 44)
    - Reference notes, miscellaneous (Box 45)
  - Miscellaneous reference notes (Box 46)
    - Franco-Prussian War (Box 46)
    - Versailles (Box 46)
    - World War I (Box 47)
    - American history (Box 48)
    - Medieval history (Box 48)
    - Opposition to the War of 1812 (Box 48)
    - Roman history (Box 48)
    - France (Box 49)
    - Anglo-Saxon law (Box 50)
    - French newspapers, 1898 (Box 50)
    - London Times, 1898, July-Sept. (Box 50)
    - American history (Box 51-52)
    - Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions (Box 53)
    - French Revolution (Box 54)
    - Modern England, Italy, Austria, and Germany (Box 54)
    - World War I (Box 54)
    - Europe (Box 55)
    - General (Box 55)
    - General (Box 56)
    - Notes used in teaching (Box 56)
    - Research reminders (Box 56)
  - Articles (Box 57)
  - Book reviews (Box 57)
  - Lectures (Box 57)
  - Papers delivered (Box 57)
  - Speeches (Box 57)